Frances Fox Piven Papers, 1957-2011
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES V. WRITINGS (circa 1962- )
  - Articles, [see APPENDIX for list of articles by subject]
    - "We Should have made a Plan!," with RAC: drafts, correspondence, and conference materials, 1996-97 (Box 80, Folder 1)
  - Undated writings
    - "Part I: The Principle of Indeterminancy;" "The Classical Paradigm as Indeterminant" (Box 80, Folder 2)
    - "Sociology's Asociological Perspective on Deviant Behavior" (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - "State Structures and Political Protest: Notes Toward a Theory" (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - "The Politics of Unemployment in the 1980s" (Box 80, Folder 5)
    - "Education Policy and the Formation of Political Consciousness" (Box 80, Folder 6)
    - "Popular Power and the Welfare State" (Box 80, Folder 7)
    - "Draft of PEO Policy Statement" (Box 80, Folder 8)
    - "Rent Strikes Now!" (Box 80, Folder 9)
    - "Low-Income People and Institutional Change" (Box 80, Folder 10)
    - "Challenging 'The Poor Law'" (Box 80, Folder 11)
    - "Dissensus Politics: A Strategy for Black Power;" "Dissensus Politics: Martin Luther King's Political Legacy" (Box 80, Folder 12)
    - Rewrite, "The Professional Bureaucracies Benefit Systems as Influence Systems" (Box 80, Folder 13)
    - "Public Planning and the Local Community" (Box 80, Folder 14)
    - Women and the State: Ideology, Power, and the Welfare State (Box 80, Folder 15)
- SERIES VI. SPEECHES (1967-1997)
  - Notes, correspondence, and publicity materials
    - 1967-1997, n.d. (Box 81-87)
    - HumanSERVE speech notes, 1984-1988, n.d. (Box 88-91)
- SERIES VII. SUBJECT FILES (circa 1950- )
  - Cuba
    - Correspondence and clippings, circa 1968-69 (Box 92, Folder 1)
    - Travel journal, Jul 23 - Aug 17 [1968?] [Kept by Piven] (Box 92, Folder 2)
    - Travel journal, Jul 27- Aug 18 [1968?] [Probably kept by Lisa Peattie?] (Box 92, Folder 3)
  - Housing
    - "Organizer Propaganda" (manuals), circa 1966 (Box 92, Folder 4)
    - Rent strike materials: printed material and clippings, 1969-70 (Box 92, Folder 5)
    - "A Plan for Borough and Neighborhood Government in New York City," 1970 (Box 92, Folder 6)
    - Tenant, 1971 (Box 92, Folder 7)
    - Tenants' First Defense Committee: informational packet, circa 1976 (Box 92, Folder 8)
    - "U.S. Housing Policy at the Crossroads: A Progressive Agenda to Rebuild the Housing Constituency," Peter Dreier, 1996 (Box 92, Folder 9)
  - New York City Population and Voting Data, 1980s (Box 92, Folder 10)
  - Readings (from graduate school?): notes, circa 1950s (Box 92, Folder 11)
  - Riots: clippings, 1967-71 (Box 92, Folder 12)
  - Segregation and education, circa 1966-67 (Box 93, Folder 1)
  - Welfare
    - Clippings, 1966-67 [includes some materials pertaining to the National Welfare Rights Organization and the Poverty/Action Center] (Box 93, Folder 2-3)
    - Federal Minimum Income Program: memoranda, clippings, and printed material, 1965-66 (Box 93, Folder 4)
    - Poor relief: notes on its history, n.d. (Box 93, Folder 5)
    - Onandaga County (NY) Dept. of Social Welfare: minutes and correspondence on welfare housing, 1966 (Box 93, Folder 6)
    - Poor/Welfare: talks, clippings, and speech notes, 1988-90 (Box 93, Folder 7)
    - NYC Welfare Reform, 1994-95 (Box 93, Folder 8)
    - "The Welfare Fighter," 1972 (Box 93, Folder 9)
    - Welfare Rights Handbooks, circa 1960s-70s (Box 93, Folder 10-11)
- SERIES VIII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIAL (1987- ), 3 linear feet.
  - Videotapes
    - Welfare reform
      - Currents, "Children in Poverty" (Child Welfare) 1 Oct 1987 (Box 94)
      - Currents, "Welfare: What's Fair?" (Welfare Reform) 5 May 1988 [Piven does not seem to appear on this broadcast] (Box 94)
      - Opening conference, McGill University, 2 Mar 1992 (Box 94)
      - CUNY TV, MetroView, "Welfare Reform: Scapegoating Women," Mar 1994 (Box 94)
      - WNYC New York Hotline, "Who Are New York's Poor?" 8 Feb 1995 (Box 94)
      - Hamline University, "The Politics of Contemporary Welfare Reform," 21 Feb 1995 (Box 94)
      - "Women in the Welfare State," Radio Free Maine, 10 May 1995 (Box 94)
      - The McNeil/Lehrer Report, "Rethinking Welfare," Jun 1995 (Box 94)
      - NewsTalk Television, "Welfare Reform," 19 Sep 1995 (Box 94)
      - The News Hour with Jim Lehrer, "America Works," 10 Oct 1997 (Box 94)
      - Welfare Warriors: VisionQuest Film and Video Productions, 1997 (Box 94)
      - Labor At the Crossroads, "Workfare, Welfare, Nightmare" (Hunter College). n.d. (Box 94)
      - Firing Line, "Resolved: Welfare Has Done More Harm Than Good," 15 Mar 1994 (Box 95)
      - CUNY-TV, "Women to Women on Welfare Reform," n.d. (Box 95)
      - CUNY-TV, "Views from the Left," n.d. (Box 95)
    - Voter turnout
      - CUNY Forum, "Election '96: What's In Store?" 12 Nov 1996 (Box 95)
      - WNYC New York Hotline, RAC on voter turnout, n.d. (Box 95)
      - CUNY TV MetroView, "The Election of 1996," n.d. (Box 95)
    - General
      - NewsTalk Television, "The American Dream," 4 May 1995 (Box 95)
      - NewsTalk Television, "Balancing the Budget," 22 Mar 1996 (several short blackouts on tape) (Box 95)
      - "Closing the Open Door: The Fight for Education" (topic: student strikes at CUNY), circa 1997 (Box 95)
      - CUNY TV, The Women's Studies Program and the Center for the Study of Women and Society at the CUNY Graduate School and University Center present "Women on Social Issues" (topic: Family Values and Political Culture), n.d. (Box 95)
      - CUNY TV, CUNY Conversations (in the aftermath of the Socialist Scholars Conference, topics include the impact of Socialism, welfare systems, the disaffected electorate, and the work ethic in American culture), n.d. (Box 95)
      - CUNY TV MetroView, "Is Washington Abandoning the Cities?" n.d. (Box 95)
  - Audiotapes
    - "Popular Power in Post-Industrial Society," CUNY Conference, February 1989: cassette tapes
      - 1)Frances Opening/Panel 1 [opening remarks, Piven] (Box 96)
      - 2)Panel 1 cont'd/Panel 2/Panel 3 (Box 96)
      - 3)End of Day/Day 2 Panel 1/Panel 2 (Box 96)
      - 4)Day 2 Panel 2/Panel 3 (Box 96)
      - 5)Panel 3/Panel 4/Panel 5/Panel 6 (Box 96)
      - 6)Sweden/Miller (Box 96)
    - "Bridges: A Liberal/Conservative Dialogue with Larry Josephson" (topic: welfare reform) (Box 96)
    - Voice of America, "Youth in the Democratic Process" (a conversation with panelists in Santiago, Chile) 17 Oct 1991 (Box 96)
    - Wisconsin Public Radio, "Ideas Network," Jan Weller (welfare reform) 14 Jun 1994 (Box 96)
    - Gil Gross Show (topic: Virginia law requiring mothers to identify fathers in order to receive welfare benefits) 4 Jun 1996 (Box 96)
    - CSWE Conference, Detroit, Opening Plenary Session 43, 11 Mar 84 [Tape is damaged] (Box 96)
    - Making Contact, "Welfare Reform and the Rural Poor," National Radio Project, 1996 (Box 96)
    - Talk of the Nation, "The Influence of Karl Marx," 1 May 1996 (Box 96)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - SERIES III. TEACHING: "Housing," notes and flow chart, "Site Production Process," 1970 (Map-case Flat File)
  - SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL and SERIES VI. SPEECHES: Publicity materials (Map-case Flat File)